Prerna **Juneja**

☑ prernajun6@gmail.com | 🎢 https://prernajuneja.com/ | 🛅 prerna-juneja-a3a5223b

Overview

A human-computer interaction researcher with 5+ years of experience in conducting interdisciplinary research across high-impact problem domains such as responsible AI, ethics, and policy. I combine AI, data-driven techniques, and human-centered design processes with large-scale real-world deployments to understand the risks of A.I. systems and tools, including generative A.I. models.

Research Interests: Human-computer interaction | Responsible AI | Designing for trust, transparency, and explainability | Online misinformation

Accomplishments and Real-World Impact:

- · Part of Open Al's Red Team Network
- U.S. Representative Adam Schiff cited my research in congressional letter
- Interviewed by the U.S. House Select Subcommittee staff about challenges of problematic algorithmic recommendations
- Research recognized by media, notably in The Seattle Times, The Guardian, Al Jazeera, etc.
- Managed and led a team of 10 researchers, designers, and engineers to design YouCred, a fact-checking tool deployed at fact-checking organization Pesacheck

Education

University of Washington

Seattle, USA

PhD in Information Science

Sep. 2020 - Aug. 2023

Adviser: Dr. Tanushree Mitra • SSRC PhD Dissertation Fellowship 2020-2021

Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, USA

PHD IN COMPUTER SCIENCE - transferred to University of Washington

Aug. 2018 - Jul. 2020

Adviser: Dr. Tanushree Mitra

IIIT Delhi

Delhi, India

MASTER OF TECHNOLOGY IN COMPUTER SCIENCE (M.TECH. CS)

Aug. 2013 - May. 2015

Adviser: Dr. Ashish Sureka

Experience

OpenAl Seattle, USA

INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR, OPENAI RED TEAMING NETWORK

Jan 2024-Present

· Participated in OpenAI led red teaming efforts to assess the risks and safety profile of OpenAI models and systems.

Seattle University Seattle, USA

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

Sept 2023-Present

Dataminr

Remote

Studied users' needs from search results explanations.

• Studied users freeds from search results explanation

University of Washington

Seattle, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

RESEARCH INTERN

Sept 2020-Aug 2023

June 2022-Sept 2022

- Conducted audits to understand the role of online algorithms in amplifying misinformation
- Worked with fact-checking organizations to understand their needs and built tools for them

Information Science Institute, USC

Remote

1

RESEARCH INTERN

May 2020-Aug 2020

• Modeled users who are susceptible to misinformative content on social media platforms.

 Dell EMC
 Bengaluru, India

 SOFTWARE ENGINEER 2
 Aug 2015-July 2018

• Designed & developed eLicense solution that helped EMC to track customer's storage usage & compliance

- Scaled and improved the performance of the user operations
- Supported VMware's VASA2.0 specifications by implementing interfaces to query storage details and perform storage manageability operations

Honors & Awards

- University of Washington Graduate School Medal Award 2023: Recognizes a Ph.D. candidate who is tackling a challenge of tremendous social importance through extraordinarily rigorous scholarship.
- Impact Recognition Award: ACM CSCW 2022
- Honourable Mention Award: ACM CSCW 2022
- Research cited in congressional letter: U.S. Representative Adam Schiff cited my Amazon audit research in his congressional letter where he asked Amazon to address the problem of vaccine misinformation

- Best Paper Honourable Mention Award: ACM CHI 2021
- SSRC Dissertation Fellowship 2020: Supports thesis work on algorithmically curated misinformation
- CRA-W Grad Cohort Grant 2019: Received scholarship to attend Grad Cohort workshop
- Excellence@Dell Bronze Award: May 2018, July 2017 and Aug 2016
- Dell Champion Award: Aug 2018
- Merit Scholarship: Awarded during 1st and 3rd year of bachelors for securing second and first position respectively

Publications

Heavily Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

- 10. **Prerna Juneja**, Wenjuan Zhang, Alison Marie Smith-Renner, Hemank Lamba, Joel Tetreault, and Alex Jaimes. Dissecting users' needs for search result explanations. *In Proc. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2024).*
- 9. Emelia May Hughes, Renee Wang, **Prerna Juneja**, Tony W Li, Tanushree Mitra, and Amy X. Zhang. Viblio: Introducing Credibility Signals and Citations to Video-Sharing Platforms. *In Proc. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2024).*
- 8. Prerna Juneja, Momen Bhuiyan, and Tanushree Mitra. Assessing enactment of content regulation policies: A post hoc crowd-sourced audit of election misinformation on YouTube. In Proc. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2023).
- 7. Prerna Juneja and Tanushree Mitra. Human and technological infrastructures of fact-checking. In Proc. ACM Human Computer Interaction, CSCW 2022. Impact Recognition Award, Honourable Mention Award (Top 3% of ACM CSCW papers)
- 6. Prerna Juneja. Identifying, measuring and contesting algorithmically curated misinformation. In Proc. ACM Human Computer Interaction, CSCW Doctoral Colloquium 2021
- 5. Prerna Juneja and Tanushree Mitra. Auditing E-Commerce Platforms for Algorithmically Curated Vaccine Misinformation. In Proc. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2021). Best Paper Honourable Mention (Top 5% of ACM CHI papers)
- 4. Eslam Hussein*, Prerna Juneja* and Tanushree Mitra. Measuring Misinformation in Video Search Platforms: An Audit Study on YouTube. * (equal contribution) In Proc. ACM Human Computer Interaction 4, CSCW1, Article 48.
- 3. Prerna Juneja, Deepika Ramasubramanian and Tanushree Mitra. Through the Looking Glass: Study of Transparency in Reddit's Moderation Practices. In Proc. GROUP 2020: ACM Conference on Supporting Group Work.
- 2. **Prerna Juneja**, Divya Kundra, and Ashish Sureka. Anvaya: An algorithm and case-study on improving the goodness of software process models generated by mining event-log data in issue tracking systems. *In Proceedings of the 40th IEEE Annual Computer Software and Applications Conference (COMPSAC), 2016.*
- 1. Divya Kundra, Prerna Juneja, and Ashish Sureka. Vidushi: parallel implementation of alpha miner algorithm and performance analysis on CPÚ and GPÚ architecture. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Business Process Management (BPM), 2016.

Workshop Papers

- 3. Emelia Hughes, Renee Wang, Prerna Juneja, Tanushree Mitra and Amy X. Zhang. Introducing Credibility Signals and Citations to YouTube. In Information Credibility Workshop at ICWSM 2021
- 2. Prerna Juneja and Tanushree Mitra. Algorithmic nudge: Using XAI frameworks to design interventions. In CHI 2021 Workshop on Operationalizina Human-centered Perspectives in Explainable Al
- 1. Prerna Juneja and Tanushree Mitra. Investigating the impact of personalization on misinformation present in algorithmically curated content in YouTube. In RecSys 2020 Workshop on Responsible Recommendation

Skills

Python, Core Java, C, C++, Javascript, Lua, Android **Programming Languages User research** Interviews, surveys, thematic analysis, stakeholder analysis **Data Analysis and Applied ML** Python: pandas, numpy, matplotlib, Seaborn, sklearn, statsmodels

Relevant Coursework Data Analytics, Social Computing, Statistics in Research, Machine Learning, Deep Learning

Mentorship

• Bryan Kim: B.S. SU: Responsible Al

• Ashleen Sandhu: B.S. SU: Responsible Al

• Lisa Lomidze: M.S. SU: Responsible AI

• David Xie: B.S. UW Informatics: Fact-checking system project

• Alice Zhang: B.S. UW CS: Fact-checking system project

• Lee Polla: MSIM UW: Fact-checking system project

• Benjamin Ye: B.S. UW CS: Fact-checking system project

• Louis Leng: B.S. UW Informatics: Fact-checking system project

• Vincent Zhiyuan Zhou: B.S. UW CS: Fact-checking system project

• Ethan Yee: B.S. UW CS: Fact-checking system project

• Srinidhi Balaram: B.S. UW Informatics: Figma design for fact-checking system project

• Emelia Hughes: B.S. UW Informatics: YouTube credibility signals and citation study

• Renee Wang: B.S. UW CS: YouTube credibility signals and citation study

• Hayoung Jung: B.S. UW CS: YouTube geolocation audit

• Stephanie L. Zhang: B.S. UW Informatics: Chrome extension to scrape users' YouTube data

• Deepika Ramasubramanian: M.S., Virginia Tech: Reddit transparency study

• Jonathan Alexander: B.S. CS Virginia Tech: Scraping Twitter feed via selenium bots

• Ankita Khera: B.S. CS Virginia Tech: Scraping data from Amazon

Summer 2024-Present

Summer 2024-Present

Fall 2023-Present

Fall 2021, Spring 2022

Spring 2022

Fall 2021, Spring 2022

Summer 2022-Dec 2022 Summer 2022-Spring 2023

Summer 2022

Summer 2022

Summer 2022

Fall 2021-Summer 2023 Fall 2021-Spring 2022

Summer 2021-Fall 2023 2020-2021

2018-2019

Fall 2019

Fall 2019

Invited Talks

April 2024 Towards understanding and defending against online misinformation, guest visit for SI 429 and SI 529, School of Information,

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

April 2022 **Problematic Information**, guest visit for IMT 598, University of Washington

September 2021 Investigating algorithms and their impacts, School of Information, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

September 2021 Auditing YouTube for conspiracy theories, Department of Computer Science, Wellesley College, Wellesley, Massachusetts

May 2021 Auditing online platforms for algorithmically curated misinformation, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Virginia

Press and Media Coverage_____

July 2024	Has YouTube failed to curb cancer-related misinformation? Logically Facts 🗹
Nov 2023	'Heavy metal detox bath' for kids: Unscientific trend catapults into 'health advice' Logically Facts 🖸
Aug 2023	Heard about the borax trend? Jumping onto it is dangerous. Logically Facts 🗗
May 2023	Inside the health books on Amazon: Pseudoscience and unsubstantiated remedies. Logically Facts
Jun 2021	The conspiracy and disinformation challenge on e-commerce platforms. Brookings Tech
Mar 2021	COVID-19: Anti-vax book sales surge as sellers urged to add warning tags. Sky News
Jan 2021	Aired on January 29, 2021 at 4:45 AM. King-TV
Jun 2021	Aired on January 29, 2021 at 7:32 AM. KOMO AM
Jan 2021	Aired on January 29, 2021 at 4:53 AM on Fox 13 Seattle. KCPQ-TV
Dec 2021	AmazonSmile donated more than \$40,000 to anti-vaccine groups in 2020. The Guardian
June 2021	How Amazon became an engine for anti-vaccine conspiracy theories. Fast Company ☑
Jan 2021	Amazon algorithms promote vaccine misinformation, UW study says. The Seattle Times
Jan 2021	Amazon's algorithms boost vaccine misinformation, says study. India Times
Jan 2021	Amazon search boosts anti-vax books. The Columbian
Jan 2021	
	Amazonovi algoritmi promiču antivakserske dezinformacije. Al Jazeera
Feb 2021	Amazon's search algorithm spreads vaccine disinformation, study finds. The Next Web
Feb 2021	Amazon is a 'marketplace of multifaceted health misinformation,' UW study says. The Daily 🖸
Jan 2021	University of Washington researchers say Amazon's algorithms spread vaccine misinformation. Venture Beat 🗗
Jan 2021	UW study finds Amazon promotes vaccine lies, especially to already misinformed users. The Spokesman Review 🗗
Nov 2020	New study finds YouTube is now suppressing anti-vaccine videos. The Hill 🔀
Nov 2020	YouTube's algorithm is steering viewers away from anti-vaccine videos Business Insider 🖸
Oct 2020	Fellowship backs Ph.D. student's research on algorithms and misinformation iNews 🖸
Sep 2020	SSRC Announces the Recipients of the Social Data Research and Dissertation Fellowships SSRC News
	·